A Finding Aid to the Alexander Archipenko Papers, 1904-1986, bulk 1930-1964, in the Archives of American Art AAA.archalex
Archives of American Art
Alexander Archipenko papers
bulk 1930-1964
1904-1986
AAA.archalex
Archives of American Art
19 Linear feet
The Alexander Archipenko papers measure 19 linear feet and date from 1904 to 1986, with the bulk of materials dating from 1930 to 1964. The sculptor's personal and professional life is documented by correspondence, financial records, scrapbooks, printed matter, and photographs documenting his art, exhibitions, travel, teaching activities, and the Archipenko Art School. Archipenko wrote and lectured extensively about his philosophies of art and the relationship between art and nature. The papers include drafts, notes, and final manuscripts of published and unpublished writings, and notes, outlines, transcripts, and audio recordings of some of his lectures.
Archipenko, Alexander, 1887-1964
Biographical Note
Alexander Archipenko (1887-1964) was the son of an engineer/inventor and grandson of an icon painter. Among the first modern sculptors of the 20th century to be associated with the Cubist movement, Archipenko was known for his innovative use of concave space. His major contribution was the realization of negative form through use of a hole to create a contrast of solid and void. His sculpto-paintings united form and color; begun in 1912, these polychromed constructions are among the earliest mixed-media works known, and sometimes incorporated objects. Eventually, his Cubist-inspired work evolved into the simplified, abstract shapes for which he is best known. Although known primarily as a sculptor, Archipenko produced paintings, drawings, and prints as well.
At age 15, Archipenko began studying art at the University of Kiev in his native city; he was expelled three years later for criticizing the teachers. He then went to Moscow where he worked on his own and exhibited in several group shows; his first solo exhibition was held in the Ukraine in 1906.
Archipenko made Paris his home from 1908 until the outbreak of World War I. Soon after his arrival, he enrolled in the Ecole des Beaux-Arts; this association lasted but two weeks, and marked the end of Archipenko's formal training. He continued to study art by spending large amounts of time visiting art museums and painting on his own. During this period, he began exhibiting in the Salon des Independents with the Cubists, and as a member of the "Section d'Or" participated in that group's exhibitions. His first one-man exhibition in Germany was held at the Folkwant Museum (1912) and his work was featured in the Armory Show (1913).
In 1912, at the age of 25, Archipenko established his first art school in Paris. He spent the war years working quietly outside of Nice, and soon afterwards circulated an extensive exhibition of his works throughout Europe. In 1921, Archipenko settled in Berlin, opened an art school there, and married sculptor Angelica Bruno-Schmitz, who was known professionally as Gela Forster.
Archipenko's reputation was solidly established and the majority of his ground-breaking work - adaptation of Cubist ideas to sculpture, sculpto-paintings and incorporation of negative space in sculpture - was accomplished prior to his 1923 arrival in the United States. One of his most innovative works executed in America was the Archipentura, invented circa 1924 and patented in 1927, a machine with rolling cylinders that displayed "animated paintings" using motion and light. Other creations of note are carved Lucite sculptures, illuminated from within, that were executed in the mid-1940s.
Upon settling in the United States in 1923, Archipenko opened his art school in New York City; a summer school was established in Woodstock, New York the following year. Within a few years, Archipenko purchased land near Woodstock and began construction of a home, personal studio, and buildings for the school. At various times during the 1930s, Archipenko resided in Chicago and Los Angeles, and operated schools while living in those cities. For many years during the 1940s, Angelica served on the sculpture faculty at the Escuela de Belles Artes in San Miguel Allende, Mexico.
In addition to running his own schools, Archipenko taught at a number of colleges and universities, where he ran workshops, and served as a visiting professor. He wrote and lectured extensively about his philosophy of art and theories of creativity, publishing several articles and a book, Archipenko: Fifty Creative Years, 1908-1958 (1960).
Angelica Archipenko died in 1957. Three years later Archipenko married sculptor Frances Gray, a former student. During the early 1960s, the couple traveled extensively on a lecture tour that accompanied a solo exhibition to several German cities. Archipenko died in New York City, February 25, 1964.
The following chronology is excerpted from Alexander Archipenko: A Centennial Tribute by Katherine Janszky Michaelsen and Nehama Guralnik (National Gallery of Art, Washington, DC, 1986) and Archipenko: The Sculpture and Graphic art, Including a Print Catalogue Raisonne by Donald Karshan, Ernst Wasmuth Verlag (Tubingen, Germany, 1974).
1887 Born to Porfiry Antonovich and Poroskovia Wassilievna Machova Archipenko in Kiev, Ukraine, Russia. Father a mechanical engineer, professor of engineering, and inventor; grandfather an icon painter.
1900 Studied and copied Michelangelo drawings from a book given him by his grandfather during a long confinement following a leg injury.
1902-1905 Painting and sculpture student in Kiev art school; expelled for criticizing his teachers.
1906 First one-man show in the Ukraine. Worked in Moscow and exhibited in several group shows.
1908 Moved to Paris and enrolled in the Ecole des Beaux-Arts. Quit formal art instruction after two weeks, continued to study art on his own by visiting museums.
1910 Exhibited in the Salon des Independants with the cubists (also in 1911-1914 and 1919).
1912 Opened art school in Paris. "Section d'Or" formed in Paris with Archipenko among its members. The group exhibited until 1914, and briefly after World War I. First solo exhibition in Germany, Folkwant Museum, Hagen.
1913 Represented in the Armory Show. Executed first prints (lithographs).
1914 Began making sculpto-paintings.
1914-1918 Spent the war years working near Nice.
1919-1920 Began extensive tour exhibiting his works in various European cities (Geneva, Zurich, Paris, London, Brussels, Athens, Berlin, Munich, etc.).
1920 One-man exhibition in the Venice Biennale.
1921 First solo exhibition in the United States at the Societe Anonyme, Inc., New York; a symposium, Psychology of Modern Art and Archipenko, was held during the course of the show. Moved to Berlin and opened art school. Married sculptor Angelica Bruno-Schmitz [known professionally as Gela Forster]. First print commission.
1923 Moved to the United States and opened art school in New York City.
1924 Established a summer school at Woodstock, New York.
1927 "Archipentura" patented ("Apparatus for displaying Changeable Pictures and methods for Decorating Changeable Display Apparatus," nos. 1,626, 946 and 1,626,497).
1928 Became an American citizen.
1929 Bought land near Woodstock, New York, and began construction of school and studio buildings.
1932 Lectured on his theories of creativeness at colleges and universities throughout the United States.
1933 Taught summer session at Mills College, Oakland, California, and Chouinard School, Los Angeles.
1935 Moved to Los Angeles and opened art school.
1935-1936 Taught summer sessions at the University of Washington, Seattle.
1936 Moved to Chicago and opened art school. Associate instructor at New Bauhaus School, Chicago.
1938 Returned to New York; reopened art school and Woodstock summer school.
1944 Taught at the Dalton School, New York City.
1946-1947 Returned to Chicago; taught at the Institute of Design.
1947 Began making carved plastic sculptures with internal illumination.
1950 Taught at University of Kansas City, Missouri.
1950-1951 Lecture tour of the southern cities of the United States.
1951 Taught at Carmel Institute of Art, California, University of Oregon, and University of Washington, Seattle.
1952 Taught at University of Delaware, Newark.
1953 Elected Associate Member of International Institute of Arts and Letters.
1955-1956 One-man exhibition tours in Germany (Dusseldorf, Darmstadt, Mannheim, and Recklinghausen).
1956 Taught at University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada.
1957 Death of Angelica.
1959 Awarded gold medal, XIII Biennale de'Arte Triveneta, III Concorso Internationale del Bronzetto, Padua, Italy.
1960 Archipenko: Fifty Creative Years, 1908-1958 by Alexander Archipenko and Fifty Art Historians published by Tekhne (a company established by Archipenko for the purpose). Married Frances Gray, a sculptor and former student. Recovered plasters of early work stored by French friends since the end of World War I. Traveling exhibition in Germany (Hagen, Münster, and Dusseldorf).
1962 Elected to the Department of Art, National Institute of Arts and Letters.
1964 Dies in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The Alexander Archipenko papers measure 19 linear feet and date from 1904 to 1986, with the bulk of materials dating from 1930 to 1964. The sculptor's personal and professional life is documented by correspondence, financial records, scrapbooks, printed matter, and photographs documenting his art, exhibitions, travel, teaching activities, and the Archipenko Art School. Archipenko wrote and lectured extensively about his philosophies of art and the relationship between art and nature. The papers include drafts, notes, and final manuscripts of published and unpublished writings, and notes, outlines, transcripts, and audio recordings of some of his lectures.
Correspondence concerns both personal and professional matters. Among Archipenko's personal correspondents are relatives and friends in the Ukraine, his wife Angelica during her extended stays in Mexico and California, and other women. Professional correspondence is with dealers, curators, scholars, collectors, colleges and universities concerning exhibitions, sales and commissions, loans, and teaching and lecture engagements.
Archipenko wrote and lectured extensively about his philosophy of art, art in nature, and theories concerning creativity and the universe. His papers include manuscripts, drafts, notes and supporting materials for his book published in 1960, Archipenko: Fifty Creative Years, 1908-1958. Similar documentation of unpublished writings, as well as notes, outlines, and some transcripts of lectures and talks are also in the series.
Records concerning the Archipenko Art School are sparse, with only one photograph of students in Berlin, 1921. Surviving records include printed matter, a cashbook, student roster, and scrapbook containing photographs, printed matter, and a typescript copy of a statement by Archipenko, "How I Teach." Most of this material focuses on the New York and Woodstock schools, with only a few items concerning Chicago. In addition, files regarding Archipenko's teaching activities at schools other than his own include course descriptions, student rosters, grades, and printed matter.
Financial records consist of banking records, paid bills, and miscellaneous items. Paid bills include invoices and receipts for art supplies, shipping, and storage. Among the miscellaneous items are price lists, royalties paid by the Museum of Modern Art for Woman Combing Her Hair, and sales records.
Nine scrapbooks contain clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, lecture notices, advertisements and brochures of the Archipenko Art School, and a small number of photographs. Printed matter consists primarily of clippings about Archipenko and exhibition catalogs with related announcements and invitations. Miscellaneous items include books about Archipenko, catalogs of museum collections containing works by Archipenko, and reproductions. Of special interest is a brochure about the Multiplex Advertising Machine that bears a similarity to the Archipentura, an "apparatus for displaying Changeable Pictures" Archipenko invented circa 1924 and patented in 1927.
Photographs are of people, Archipenko's travels and miscellaneous places, exhibitions, works of art, events, and miscellaneous subjects. Five photograph albums mainly document travels. Slides and transparencies include black and white lantern slides probably used to illustrate lectures.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 10 series. Lantern slides and glass plates are housed separately and closed to researchers, but listed where they fall intellectually within the collection.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1908-1964 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1, OV 28)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1922-1970 (4.1 linear feet; Boxes 1-5)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1940-1958 (6 folders; Box 5)
Series 4: Writings, 1923-1971 (3.1 linear feet; Boxes 5-8)
Series 5: Teaching, 1921-1952 (0.5 linear feet; Box 9)
Series 6: Financial Records, 1923-1971 (1.5 linear feet; Box 9-10)
Series 7: Scrapbooks, 1910-1961 (1.2 linear feet; Boxes 22-25)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1913-1987 (3.7 linear feet; Boxes 11-14, 26, OV 29)
Series 9: Miscellaneous, 1916-1966 (0.4 linear feet; Box 14, 16)
Series 10: Photographic Material, 1904-1964 (3.6 linear feet; Boxes 14-15, 17-21, 26-27)
Related Material
The bulk of the Alexander Archipenko papers were originally loaned for microfilming and most of that material was included in later gifts and are described in this finding aid. Loaned material that was not included in later gifts is still available to researchers on reels NA11-NA12, NA16-NA18, and NA 20-NA22, but is not further described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Among the holdings of the Archives are the Donald H. Karshan papers relating to Alexander Archipenko, originally accessioned as part of the Alexander Archipenko papers, but later separated to form a distinct collection.
The Archives also has the National Collection of Fine Arts records relating to Alexander Archipenko.
Provenance
In 1967, the Alexander Archipenko papers, previously on deposit at Syracuse University, were loaned to the Archives of American Art for microfilming by his widow Frances Archipenko Gray. In 1982, Ms. Gray donated most of the material previously loaned and microfilmed to the Archives of American Art, along with additional items.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. research facility. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. Lantern slides and glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 5826-5839, and NA11-NA12, NA16-NA18 and NA20-NA22 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid may not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Archipenko Art School (Woodstock, N.Y.).; Archipenko, Angelica; Archipenko, Frances; Spies, Walter; Art--Philosophy; Art--Study and teaching; Cubism; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sculptors; Sculpture, Modern--20th century; Sculpture--Technique; Sound recordings; Transcripts
- Biographical Material, 1908-1964; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, OV 28
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include a wide variety of records concerning Alexander Archipenko, his first wife, Angelica Archipenko (an artist known professionally as Gela Forster), and his second wife, Frances Archipenko Gray (a.k.a. Frances Gray Archipenko). Among these records are ephemera, funeral guest registers, and real estate records including floor plans of their house in Woodstock, N.Y. and a proposed bequest to the Ukrainian Art and Literary Club. There are also various legal documents, including residency permits issued during Archipenko's years in France, passports, and wills. Articles by and about Angelica Archipenko include an article about Bali (in German), her art and acting careers, and exhibition and drama reviews; also included is a color reproduction of her portrait by Leo Katz. A catalog of Escuela Universitaria de Bellas Artes in San Allende, Mexico, describes the sculpture course taught by Angelica Archipenko and contains photographs of students' work. There is a recorded and transcribed interview with Angelica on a sound tape reel (1/4 in.), and Angelica's reminiscences of Walter Spies and excerpts from her diaries are also included. There are also exhibition catalogs and a will in the materials related to Frances Archipenko Gray.
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged as 3 subseries.
  1.1: Alexander Archipenko, 1908-1964
  1.2: Angelica Archipenko, 1919-1957
  1.3: Frances Archipenko Gray, 1961-1964
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Use of archival audio recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
  - Alexander Archipenko, 1908-1964; 1.1
    - Automobile Registration, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Award of Honor, Wisdom Society, circa 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biographical Notes, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Exhibitor's Admission Ticket, International Fine Arts Exposition, Brussels, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Floor Plans, 243-45 West 19th Street, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Oversized material housed in OV 28.
    - Floor Plans of Woodstock House with Map of Property, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Funeral Guest Register and Receipts, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Guest Register for 50th Anniversary of Archipenko's Career (in Ukrainian), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Handprint, circa 1940-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Legal Documents Concerning Residence in France, 1908-1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Marriage Certificate, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Membership Certificates, 1953, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Passports, 1923-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Real Estate Records, 274-6 West 19th Street, New York City, 1956, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Real Estate Records, Woodstock, 1929-1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Will, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Oversized Floor Plans 243-45 West 19th Street from Box 1, Folder 5, 1955-1956 (Box OV 28)
      5 blueprints and 3 drawings
  - Angelica Archipenko, 1919-1957; 1.2
    - Articles by and about Angelica Archipenko (a.k.a Gela Forster), 1919-1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Birth Certificate (duplicate), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Calling Card, circa 1940-1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Catalog of Escuela Universitaria de Bellas Artes, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Exhibition Label, Artists for Victory, Inc., circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Funeral Guest Register, Receipts, etc.; Dedication of Memorial Statue, 1957, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Handprint, circa 1940-1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Naturalization Certificate (duplicate), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Passports, 1923, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Poem, "To Angelica", 1954 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Interview with Angelica Archipenko, circa 1957; 1 sound tape reels Includes transcript. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Side 1 of the recording is a lecture on theology by Dr. Searl, May 20, 1957.
    - Reminiscences of Walter Spies and Related Excerpts from the Diaries of Angelica Archipenko, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Social Security Certificate, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Frances Archipenko Gray, 1961-1964; 1.3
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Will, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1922-1968; Series 2; 4.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-5
  This series, arranged chronologically, includes both personal and professional correspondence. Among the personal correspondents are relatives and friends in the Ukraine, Archipenko's wife Angelica during her extended stays in California and Mexico, and other women. Professional correspondence is with dealers, curators, scholars, collectors, colleges and universities concerning exhibitions, sales and commissions, loans, teaching, and lecture engagements. Also included are routine requests from prospective students for information about the Archipenko School or summer courses. Correspondence post-dating Archipenko's death concerns exhibitions, sales, and unfinished business.
  Additional correspondence is included with Series 3: Subject Files, which includes significant correspondence with the Museum of Modern Art and others concerning "?That is Why I Request to Remove My Art from the Museum of Modern Art by Alexander Archipenko," 1943-1944.
  - A Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - A. Ottavino, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Akademie der Kunst, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Akron Art Institute, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Altenheim, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Amherst College, 1949-1958 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Anna L. Werbe Galleries, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Archipenko, Alexander, 1939-1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Archipenko, Angelica, 1929-1964 (Box 1, Folder 40-42)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1937-1956 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Atamanetz, Ivan, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Au Pont des Arts, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - B Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Baltimore Museum of Art, 1939-1963 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Beechhurst Press, Inc., 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Beyers, Bernice, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Biennale D'Arte Triveneta, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Biennale di Venezia, 1954-1960 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Blohm, Ernesto, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Bollman, Mari, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Bowdain College Museum of Fine Arts, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Brandt, Paul, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, Albright Art Gallery, 1939-1954 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - C Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Cafritz, Edward A., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Chapelsky, Leo, 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Cincinnati Art Museum, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Ciriche Raccolte D'Arte, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - City of Auckland Art Gallery, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Civilta Delle Macchine, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Cleveland Institute of Art, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1937-1956 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Columbia University, 1939-1962 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Columbus Art League, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Conference Board of Associated Research Councils, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Cooper Union, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1931-1954 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Curro, Giuliano Vismara, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - D Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Das Kunstwerk Redaktion, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Denver Art Museum, 1940-1958 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1935-1949 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Drian Gallery, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Dzus, William, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - E Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - E. Weyhe Gallery, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Editions du Griffon, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Esposizione Nazionale Quadriennale D'Arte di Roma, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ente Premi Roma, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
  - Estorick, Eric, 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Expositions Internationales des Beaux-Arts Bruxelles (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - F Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fairmont Park Art Association, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ferrari, Ettore Gian, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fine Arts Society of San Diego, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Fondazione Pagani, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)